Women Art Revolution: videotape interviews by Lynn Hershman-Leeson M1639
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Women Art Revolution: videotape interviews by Lynn Hershman-Leeson
1990-2008
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Hershman-Leeson, Lynn
M1639
4 Linear Feet: 68 video tapes, one box of transcripts, one box of releases & transcripts, one hard drive
Videotaped interviews with over 40 artists, critics, historians, and curators for the film !Women Art Revolution, documenting the development of the feminist art movement from the 1970s through 2008.
Acquisition Information
Purchased September, 2008; Accession 2008-242.
Scope and Contents note
The collection consists of artist, critic, and curator interviews and footage created for use in the documentary !Women Art Revolution made by Lynn Hershman-Leeson, which chronicles the birth and evolution of the Feminist Art movement in the United States. The collection came as both the original videotapes of various formats and digital video file versions of most of the tapes, except where otherwise noted. The collection also includes transcripts for many of the interviews in both paper and digital form.
All received digital video files as well as any associated transcripts can be accessed through the collection website: https://exhibits.stanford.edu/women-art-revolution.
Lacy, Suzanne; Hershman-Leeson, Lynn; Leduc, Violette; Baca, Judith Francisca; Brodsky, Judith K.; Levrant de Bretteville, Sheila; Hershman-Leeson, Lynn; Kollwitz, Kathe; Vicuna, Cecilia; Hammond, Harmony; Grode, Susan A.; Guerrilla Girls; Kanarek, Yael; Kelley, Mike; Heiss, Alanna; July, Miranda; Lippard, Lucy R.; Pindell, Howardena; Antoni, Janine; Kozloff, Joyce; Antin, Eleanor; Kushner, Robert; Schneemann, Carolee; Sackler, Elizabeth A.; Schapiro, Miriam; Utterback, Camille; Wilding, Faith; Ringgold, Faith; Rosenthal, Rachel; Rosler, Martha; Roth, Moira; Sims, Lowery Stokes; Fox, Howard; Rainer, Yvonne; Reilly, Maura; Rich, B. Ruby; Wilson, Martha; Butler, Cornelia H.; Chicago, Judy; Tucker, Marcia; Da Costa, Beatriz; Spero, Nancy; Edelson, Mary Beth
- Interviews
  - Eleanor Antin
    Biography
    Eleanor Antin (b. 1935) is a performance artist, photographer, and filmmaker whose work has often explored the social constructions of gender and feminity. In the early 1970s, she began utilizing the tools of Conceptual art—especially serial photography and performance documentation—to insert social commentary, biographical representation, and fantasy into a discourse that had until then been much more focused upon the systematic and the semiotic. Carving a Traditional Sculpture (1972), for example, consisted of 144 gridded photographs of a nude Antin, arranged chronologically to document her weight loss over thirty-six days. History—and women's place in it—has been an important theme. Eleanor Antinova, her most well known and long-lived performative persona, was a fictional, marginalized member of the celebrated Ballets Russes and a demonstration of continuing gender and racial inequalities. 100 Boots (1971-73), a classic work of Conceptual art, featured 51 images of boots in scenes that progressed from one American coast to the other.
    Antin's later work has tended to incorporate quasi-historical themes; her recent photographic series include Roman Allegories (2004) and The Last Days of Pompeii (2001).
    - Santa Monica, CA; 2006-07-22 (Box 1, Videotape 1A)
      Format
      Mini-DV (1A), Digital .mov file
  - Janine Antoni
    Janine Antoni (b. 1964) is a performance artist, sculptor, and photographer who often explores the transitions between making and finished product—a focus that results in sculptural installations that appear both static and revelatory of the artist's creative process. Gnaw (1992) and Lick and Lather (1993) are two of her most well known works. In both, Antoni used materials in which she could leave lasting human marks: in Gnaw, she presented two Minimalist cubes—one of chocolate, the other of lard—that she had chewed away into deliberate deformity. In Lick and Lather, she ingested chocolate self-portrait busts and washed away soap ones into varying degrees of obscurity. These and other works—messy, unsterile—have caused viewers to re-envision the bodiliness of both abstract and figural forms; to acknowledge that feminine discretion (especially to keep body fluids hidden and their sources undisclosed) has long been a cultural expectation. Loving Care (1993) took these notions to an extreme, the piece consisting of the visual and physical remnants of Antoni's sweeping of her dye-filled hair, like a paint brush but much more personal, across a gallery floor.
    In approaching her work in this way, Antoni has adopted a project that has motivated many activist, feminist artists both of her generation and earlier: to acknowledge the feminine body and to celebrate it.
    - Brooklyn, NY; 2006-05-10 (Box 1, Videotape 2A-2B)
      Mini-DV (2A-2B), Digital .mov file
  - Judith Baca
    Judith (Judy) Baca (b. 1946), a Mexican-American artist and activist working primarily in Los Angeles, has dedicated her career to demonstrating the ways in which public art, created in partnership with community members, can be a force for social change. One of her first undertakings after college was a collaborative mural project aimed at tempering gang violence (1969). In 1976 she co-founded the Social and Public Art Resource Center (SPARC), which has been a source of inspiration, support, and sponsorship for projects that address the identities and concerns of underrepresented populations such as women, immigrants, and the economically disadvantaged. Because these murals and related public art installations are located in the neighborhoods in which the participants live, a strong sense of joint ownership accompanies the works' creation.
    Baca's most celebrated work is The Great Wall of Los Angeles, a mural project begun in 1973 in the Tujunga Flood Control Channel of the San Fernando Valley. Completed over the course of five years, The Great Wall acts as a visual narrative of centuries of California history—especially of that history which has consistently been underrepresented in "official" documents and textbooks. It, and Baca's mural projects in general, find their stylistic precedents in the works of the Mexican muralists and the W.P.A., yet the social activism and specific themes that they espouse are decidedly contemporary.
    - Catalina Island, CA; 1992-10-02 (Box 1, Videotape 3A, 3A-copy)
      Hi-8 (3A), U-matic (3A-copy), Digital .mov file
  - Judith Baca and Suzanne Lacy
    - Los Angeles, CA; 2004-07-07 (Box 1, Videotape 3B, 6A)
      DVCAM (3B, 6A), Digital .mov file
  - Judith Brodsky
    Judith K. Brodsky (b. 1933) is a noted artist and art educator. She is a Distinguished Professor Emerita in the Department of Visual Arts at Rutgers, and the Founding Director of the Rutgers Center for Innovative Print and Paper, which was renamed the Brodsky Center in her honor in September 2006.
    Over the past thirty years, Brodsky has held numerous leadership positions in the art world, most notably as past national president of ArtTable, the College Art Association, and the Women's Caucus for Art (WCA). The WCA was established in 1972 as part of the College Art Association to promote equity for women artists and art professionals. Today it remains one of the largest and most influential organizations for women artists, with twenty-seven chapters nationwide. As the first working artist to lead the organization, Brodsky expanded political activism and membership in the WCA.
    - New York, NY; 2008-04-22
      Digital .mov file
  - Cornelia (Connie) Butler
    Cornelia (Connie) Butler is the Robert Lehman Foundation Chief Curator of Drawings at the Museum of Modern Art. Prior to coming to New York in 2006, she served as a curator at the Museum of Contemporary Art, Los Angeles. Though much of Butler's curatorial focus has been directed toward works on paper and the graphic arts, perhaps her most notable project of late was the ambitious, multimedia undertaking WACK!: Art and the Feminist Revolution. Her final exhibition for MOCA, WACK! served as a retrospective exploration of the effects that feminist art of the 1970s had on the art and society that surrounded it. The show achieved a multifaceted success: high attendance numbers and an intense critical response, both positive and negative.
    - Los Angeles, CA; 2004-07-07 (Box 1, Videotape 4A)
      DVCAM (4A), Digital .mov file
    - New York, NY; 2008-02-17
  - Judy Chicago
    Judy Chicago's (b. 1939) Dinner Party (1973-79) is certainly the most iconic feminist artwork of the decade, but the artist's accomplishments are much broader than a single artwork can suggest. Having begun her career as a painter and sculptor in the late modernist vein, she radically varied the course of her career in the early 1970s by adopting an overtly feminist, and often sexual, iconography for her own work. In partnership with Miriam Schapiro she established the Feminist Art Program at the California Institute of the Arts, which opened in 1972. It was meant to serve as a place for young female artists to discover a new way of making art, removed from the entrenched male-centrism that she asserted occupied most art schools. A notable result of this program's establishment was the organization of Womanhouse, a collaborative space occupied by female artists working in various media. The Feminist Studio Workshop, which she founded with Sheila de Bretteville and Arlene Raven and which was not affiliated with CalArts, opened in 1973.
    In parallel with her artistic and pedagogical endeavors, Chicago published Through the Flower, a work that has become a touchstone for feminist autobiographical writing of the 1970s. Beyond the Flower is a sequel of sorts, describing her post-1970s life and the evolution of both her career and her views on the place of women in society.
    - Hayward, CA; 1990-11-09 (Box 1, Videotape 5A-5C)
      U-matic (5A, 5B, 5C), Digital .mov files (3)
    - Davis, CA; 2005-03-04 (Box 1, Videotape 5H)
      Mini-DV (5H), Digital .mov file
  - Beatriz da Costa
    - Los Angeles, CA; 2004-07-07 (Box 1, Videotape 6A)
      DVCAM (6A)
  - DISBAND performance
    - New York, NY; 2008-02-28
      Existence and Location of Originals note
      The DISBAND performance begins at 00:06:36 and ends at 00:18:18 on the PS 1 digital file.
  - Mary Beth Edelson
    Mary Beth Edelson (b. 1933) creates works that impel viewers to confront the feminine body and the ways in which it has been both exploited and underrepresented in the history of art. One of her primary strategies has been to portray women as primordial archetypes—created before the establishment of patriarchal societies—such as goddesses, tricksters, and warriors. She demonstrated this most famously in her series of black-and-white self portraits in which she drew and painted on nude photographs of herself posed atop boulders, in the woods, or in the undefined zone of a gallery space. By presenting herself so self-possessed and unapologetically unclothed, she hoped to help loosen the centuries-old grip that male artists held on the passive female body.
    Another one of her tactics has been to re-present famous artworks collaged with the faces and bodies of women. In Some Living American Woman Artists/Last Supper (1972), for example, Edelson covered the faces of Da Vinci's Last Supper attendees with images of contemporary female artists, Jesus being represented here by Georgia O'Keeffe. As with many of her works, Edelson combined humor and gravity, aiming to create an atmosphere that was subversively assertive.
    Edelson has also worked in collaborative and/or political environments, participating in the early exhibitions at A.I.R. Gallery (founded in 1972), taking part in the Heresies Collective, and helping to lead the Women's Action Coalition from 1992-94.
    - New York, NY; 2007-02-07 (Box 1, Videotape 8A-8B)
      Mini-DV (8A, 8B), Digital .mov files (2)
  - Howard Fox
    Howard Fox is former Curator of Contemporary Art at the Los Angeles County Museum of Art. During his tenure there he documented developments in the art world of both international and local interest, often with commendably thorough treatment of women artists and their unique contributions. Avant-Garde in the Eighties (1987) was a broadly focused show that included the work of artists such as Laurie Anderson, Cindy Sherman, Sherrie Levine, and Susan Rothenberg. Los Angeles, 1955-1985: Birth of an Art Capital (2006), held at the Centre Pompidou, provided a sweeping, chronological look at the city's unique identity in the postmodern art world—including the central role its residents played in the advancement of the feminist art movement.
    - Los Angeles, CA; 2004-07-07 (Box 1, Videotape 9A)
      DVCAM (9A), Digital .mov file
  - Susan Grode
    - Los Angeles, CA; 2004-07-07 (Box 1, Videotape 10A)
      DVCAM (10A), Digital .mov file
  - Guerrilla Girls
    Active in New York and elsewhere from 1985 to the present, the Guerrilla Girls are an anonymous group of artists, critics, and other art world participants who draw attention to disparities in treatment and pay between male and female artists and between white artists and their non-white peers. Members maintain their anonymity—important for keeping their messages broad and their professional identities safe—by the trademark donning of gorilla masks and by the adoption of female artist pseudonyms.
    The distribution of posters across SoHo and the East Village was the Guerrilla Girls' first strategic action, soon followed by protests, speaking engagements, and surprise appearances. One poster (1988), for example, declared that "the advantages of being a woman artist" included "working without the pressure of success" and "not having to undergo the embarrassment of being called a genius." Another (1990) presented a pop quiz: "Q: If February is Black History Month and March is Women's History Month, what happens the rest of the year? A: Discrimination." Combining simple graphics, clear yet clever statements, and illustrative statistics, the posters were created in order to target the art system at its epicenter, New York City. The Guerrilla Girls have more recently expanded their focus to California, Spain, Mexico, China, and elsewhere.
    - New York, NY; 2006-05-13 (Box 1, Videotapes 11B-copy, 11C-11E)
      DVCAM (11B-copy), Mini-DV (11C, 11D, 11E), Digital .mov files (4)
  - Guerrilla Girls-Kathe Kollwitz
    - Santa Monica, CA; 2006-07-22 (Box 1, Videotape 11A-copy)
      DVCAM (11A-copy), Digital .mov file
  - Guerrilla Girls-Violette Leduc
    - New York, NY; 2008-02-15
  - Harmony Hammond
    Harmony Hammond (b. 1944) has, throughout her career, actively combined her work as an artist with her goals as an activist. The artwork she has produced is grounded in the assertion that traditionally feminine qualities—emotionality, bodiliness, domesticity—are worthy subjects, and also means, for art making. The sculptural pieces she created in the early 1970s featured swaths of fabric as a primary material; her series of rag rugs from the same years evoked the products of traditional women's handwork. Her paintings, while almost exclusively abstract, are strongly textured and colored and reveal the processes of their making. Hammond asserts that this creative process, a specific experience for the female artist, is an important component of the finished object's meaning.
    Much of Hammond's work as an activist has taken place in museums and galleries. She was a founding member of A.I.R. Gallery, a female artist-run organization focused exclusively upon work by women. In 1978 she curated "A Lesbian Show" at 122 Green Street Workshop, through which she featured work by lesbian artists. Bringing attention to the unique and empowered qualities of feminist and lesbian art is a goal she has realized through the written word as well: Lesbian Art in America: A Contemporary History (2000) is the foremost text on the subject.
    - New York, NY; 2008-02-17
  - Alanna Heiss
    Alanna Heiss (b. 1943) is the Director of AIR, Art International Radio, an Internet-based art radio station operating out of the Clocktower Gallery in New York. She founded and was the Director of P.S. 1 Contemporary Art Center from 1976-2008 and is one of the originators of the so-called alternative space movement. Heiss has curated and/or organized over seven hundred exhibitions at P.S.1 and elsewhere. Considered one of the most important curatorial figures in the art world, Heiss has been awarded numerous prizes, including the Chevalier of Arts and Letters in 1987.
    - New York, NY; 2008-05-01
  - Lynn Hershman Leeson
    Lynn Hershman Leeson (b. 1941) is a performance artist and filmmaker who, in various media, has investigated the idea of selfhood and what establishes an individual as a sentient, gendered, unique person. Between the years of 1974 and 1978, Hershman Leeson spent much of her time performing as an alter ego, the character Roberta Breitmore. Much of the work—drawings, photographs, clothing, medical records, letters, etc.—Hershman Leeson produced during the Breitmore years related to the character's emotional and practical existences. Hershman Leeson seemed to be demonstrating that the two existences could and should not be easily separated—nor should the artist herself be easily separated from the character she created.
    Hershman Leeson's work in film, video, and new media has been equally focused toward exploring the ways that bodies interact and define themselves. Lorna (1983-84), described by the artist as "the first interactive video art disc," allowed the viewer to experience the emotions of the title character while also, at key points, making important decisions for her. The viewer was both entwined with and removed from Lorna's life.
    In the 1980s and 90s, Hershman continued to focus on new media, expanding her work in video and creating online environments that incorporated artificial intelligence. Concurrently, she began to direct feature films; her first film, Conceiving Ada (1997), situated the nineteenth-century computer science innovator Ada Lovelace in juxtaposition with the twentieth-century computer reality that she helped to create.
    A winner of numerous awards and honors for her contributions to art practice, Hershman Leeson is currently Chair of the Film Department at the San Francisco Art Institute. She is Professor Emerita at the University of California, Davis, and an A.D. White Professor at large at Cornell University. !Women Art Revolution reflects years of interviews that Hershman Leeson has compiled in order to tell the story of the feminist art movement in the artists' own words.
    - Davis, CA; 2005-03-04 (Box 1, Videotape 12A)
      Mini-DV (12A), Digital .mov file
    - San Francisco, CA; 2006-10-24
      The 2006 Lynn Hershman interview begins at 00:06:33 in the B. Ruby Rich part 2 interview digital video file.
  - Miranda July
    Miranda July (b. 1974) is a video and performance artist, filmmaker, and author who has attracted audiences in venues ranging from mainstream movie theaters (Me and You and Everyone We Know (2005)) to the Venice Biennale (Eleven Heavy Things (2009)). Though the themes around which she creates her work are varied—childhood, friendship, surveillance, love, control—one particularly unifying element is July's attention to her audience, real or imagined. In Things We Don’t Understand and Definitely Are Not Going to Talk About (2006– ), for example, members of the audience take active part in the performance. More subtly, Getting Stronger Every Day (2001), a seven-minute video piece, relates the deeply personal experiences of the fictional characters while also generating a quiet mood of memory and loss that resonates with any viewer. July's writing, which includes short stories and personal essays, continues this inclusive strategy. Most notable are No One Belongs Here More Than You (2007) and Learning to Love You More (2007), the titles themselves implying the participation and importance of an unknown individual(s), their accompanying Web sites inviting interaction of a different sort.
    July's relationship to the feminist artists of the previous generation is indirect yet distinct. The issues of politics and power that infuse many of her works are informed by the spirit of radical protest that surrounded her in Berkeley, where she spent her youth and began her career as an artist.
    - Santa Monica, CA; 2006-07-27 (Box 1, Videotape 11A-copy)
      This interview is on the same videotape and in the same digital video file as the Guerrilla Girl "Kathe Kollwitz" interview. Miranda July interview begins at approximately 00:39:17.
  - Yael Kanarek
    - New York, NY; 2006-05-12, 1 item(s) (Box 1, Videotape 14A)
      Mini-DV (14A)
  - Mike Kelley
    Mike Kelley is an installation, performance, and video artist who lives and works in Los Angeles. As a graduate student at the California Institute of the Arts (CalArts) between the years of 1976 and 1978, he was exposed to the feminist aesthetic and attitude that had flourished there in the early 1970s under the leadership of Judy Chicago and Miriam Schapiro. Though Kelley does not consider his work to be directly influenced by the styles and strategies of feminist art, he does cite its performative and cooperative aspects, its adoption of traditionally feminine craft materials, and its attention to social, sexual, and psychological issues as important for his own growth as an artist.
    Sculptural installations that incorporate used stuffed animals in odd, conjoined arrangements are perhaps Kelley's most well known works. These animal sculptures have often struck viewers as unsettling and somehow both personal and repellent, reactions that the artist has spent much time exploring and, at times, consciously exploiting. Other works, such as the video/installation Day is Done (2005), present a panoply of popular culture visual markers; in Day is Done these relate to the extracurricular activities associated with high school.
    Kelley's mode is often cross-disciplinary. As a young man in Detroit he played in the rock band Destroy All Monsters; musical collaborations and the punk sub-culture continue to inform his aesthetic. His writing, a substantial component of his oeuvre, ranges from art criticism to psychological musings to performative texts.
    - Los Angeles, CA; 2006-07-27 (Box 1, Videotape 15A)
      Mini-DV (15A), Digital .mov files (2)
  - Joyce Kozloff
    Born in 1942, Joyce Kozloff was a co-founder of the Pattern and Decoration movement of the 1970s. Her early paintings and collages draw on colors and designs from Islamic, North African and Southwest American Indian cultures. Kozloff's interest in decorative arts and "craft" or "ornament" aligned with the feminist movement and provided a stark alternative to the minimalist "high art" being produced mainly by men during this period. Her later large-scale public art commissions incorporate ceramic tile installations which reflect her continuing interest in color, pattern, and design from other parts of the world. Her latest cartographic works incorporate images of maps and continue to explore the themes of place, gender and power.
    - New York, NY; 2006-05-11 (Box 1, Videotape 16A)
      Mini-DV (16A), Digital .mov file
  - Robert Kushner